in this exercise we're given some code
and asked to figure out what's wrong
with it
right now we know that it causes an
infinite loop
so an infinite loop is a loop that just
keeps going forever and ever and never
stops if i run this file the loop will
continually iterate and i'll have to
force quit the program in the terminal
with something like control or command c
i can actually show you that if we run
the file and
get ready for a bunch of output ones
as you can see it's just going to keep
going and going and going until i force
it to stop
and there's plenty of output here for us
to look at
it's
quite a bit
so let's evaluate this code and figure
out what is going wrong with it the
first thing we're doing is declaring
this variable counter in the top level
scope and initializing it to the value
0.
and then next we have this while loop on
lines 3 through 10 and what a while loop
does is it will continually execute as
long as the conditional expression we
provide it returns a truthy value
in this case the conditional expression
we are providing on line three
is reassigning the value of the variable
counter to one
this is tricky because reassignment
expressions always return the value
that's being assigned and in this case
that value is 1 which is truthy
therefore this expression will always
return a truthy value and the loop will
never stop executing
we might think that
because we're incrementing counter on
line 5 that eventually this break
statement on line 8 should execute and
we should get out of the loop but the
problem here is that because while has
to evaluate this expression each time we
iterate through the loop counter is
getting reassigned to one every time the
loop iterates which means that on line 5
counter is getting reassigned to 2. line
7 needs counter to be greater than 2 to
return true so this break statement will
never get run because as soon as we get
down here we go back up to the top and
counter is reassigned again to 1.
so that's what happens when you have an
infinite loop